BU Records: Pi Gamma Mu, Inclusive: 1924-1968, undated.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Pi Gamma Mu
Inclusive: 1924-1968, undated.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/133
Pi Gamma Mu, 1924 - Unknown
8 folders.
BU Records: Pi Gamma Mu covers the founding of the Texas Beta Chapter on campus and its 40 years of activity. Papers include correspondence, handbooks and club initiation guides, information on members, and organizational histories.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Pi Gamma Mu is a collegiate honor society for students studying the social sciences. It was founded in 1924 by Dr. Leroy Allen, who was the head of the economics department at Southwestern College in Winfield, Kansas. The organization quickly spread throughout the country and in 1981 it became an international organization with the establishment of a chapter at the University of the Philippines. Pi Gamma Mu has also published a journal since 1925, when it was originally called Social Science. It was changed in 1981 to the International Social Science Review. The organization also supports the studies of members by providing academic scholarships. Currently, there are over 150 chapters in the United States and abroad.
The Texas Beta Chapter of Pi Gamma Mu was charted at Baylor University on 1924 December 1 after Charlie D. Johnson reached out to the society for recognition. Johnson would also become the organization’s first secretary. The organization operated on campus until its dissolution sometime after 1968.
Scope and Content
The collection begins in 1924 and ends in 1968, with some undated materials.The materials detail the day-to-day running of the organization as well club history and rituals through its four decades on Baylor’s campus. There are two series within this collection, entitled Correspondence and Chapter Files. Correspondence contains letters between officers of the Baylor chapter and the national organization. Chapter Files contains materials related to history, events, members, and procedures of the chapter itself. The condition of the collection is good.
Some materials in the collection were compiled by previous Texas Collection staff members over time and kept in subject files. These materials were added to the collection during processing.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection was arranged in no particular order in labeled and unlabeled folders. Currently, the collection is arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, II. Chapter Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/133. Acquired 1974-10-31
Related Resources
Related references
BU Records: Pi Gamma Mu, Box 1, Folder 5, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
"The Pi Gamma Mu Story". Pi Gamma Mu. Accessed 2019 August 30.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Societies, etc.
Subjects
Greek letter societies -- Texas -- Waco.; Greek letter societies -- United States.; Greek letter societies.; Records (Documents); Social sciences -- Societies, etc.; Students -- Societies, etc.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1944-1968, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence between members of the Texas Beta chapter of Pi Gamma Mu as well as correspondence between the chapter and the national organization. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1944-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chapter Files, 1924-1968, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains club materials such as handbooks, histories, membership details, ritual information, and newspaper clippings related to the Texas Beta Chapter of the Pi Gamma Mu fraternity. This series is in good condition.
  - Clippings, 1926-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Event Invitations and Programs, 1943-1968,undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Handbook, 1936-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "A History of Texas Beta Chapter of Pi Gamma Mu, A Social Science Fraternity", 1924-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Initiation and Ritual Information, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership Information, 1926-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Pi Gamma Mu: The National Social Science Honor Society" by Jeanette Tucker, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)